Okay, so we're on the fifth פרק Perek and we pick up
at the bottom of מ"ו ע"ב. Mem Vav Amud Bet. We have
moved beyond the fourth פרק Perek focused a lot on שור תם
Shor Tam and שור מועד Shor Muad and now we're dealing with
some more general issues that relate to the goring ox and in
other cases as we'll see in the upcoming משנה Mishnah and the
big case of the first משנה Mishnah is the case of ספק,
Safek, of a doubt. You don't know whether the cow was gored
when it was pregnant or not, so does the owner have to
pay for it? So the position of the משנה Mishnah of סומכוס
Sumchos is you split it, you split the payment for the fetus
which might have been gored by the ox or not, and the
חכמים Chachamim would say המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. Hamotzi mechavero alav haraya.
Now we're dealing with the second part of the משנה Mishnah which
is less clear, which is that the cow gored and you don't
know if the cow was pregnant or not, and it says also
the similar idea of split, you say you pay half damages from
the cow and half from the fetus. You don't know if the
fetus was part of the goring cow or not, but of course
and you pay a quarter of the fetus, but that does not
seem to make sense, it sounds like three quarters damages. אביי Abaye
basically says the issue is is that the fetus is owned by
a different person
and therefore you don't know and you get so you take half
of what you should have been paid, half of the half damages.
If the full damages were two hundred you're owed a hundred, you
get half of that from the goring ox because that ox was
definitely one of the guilty parties, one of the perpetrators.
And the question is is do you collect your other half? If
you knew for sure that the fetus was part of it you'd
collect your other half from the fetus. Because you don't know for
sure you split it, you get half of the half. Okay, that
was the position of אביי Abaye and along the way we pointed
out two things that תוספות Tosafot says. Number one is is that
even if the fetus was part of the cow, it's presumably to
be divided half and half, the fetus was only a small part
of the animal that did the damage. תוספות Tosafot says speaking about
half is just speaking like it's a representative number but what it
really means is whatever the proportional amount would be, that's the responsibility
of the fetus and since you don't know you only get half
of that. And the other interesting thing was was that you don't
say that look, yes maybe even if they both did do it
if one of them isn't around to collect from maybe I should
be able to collect the balance from the other. And according to
this no, you only get like let's say it's a ninety ten
split, you only if you can't get your ten percent out of
the fetus then you cannot take more than your ninety percent out
of the cow. And that's something we're going to see later when
there are multiple participants in the damage, do you is it like
a fifty fifty split or is it a hundred hundred how do
you exactly imagine how to divide the responsibility. Okay, now the גמרא
Gemara picks up at the bottom of
מ"ו ע"ב. Mem Vav Amud Bet. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so רבא
Rava says, אטו אחד מארבעה בנזק ואחד משמונה בנזק קתני? Atu achad
me-arba'ah be-nezek ve-achad mi-shmonah be-nezek katani? And אביי Abaye
you said where the משנה Mishnah said a half and a quarter
it meant a half of what you would be liable which is
really a quarter of the total. And when it said a quarter
it meant a quarter of what you should be liable, a quarter
of the half which meant an eighth of the total. But that's
not what the משנה Mishnah said. The משנה Mishnah didn't say a
quarter and an eighth. The משנה Mishnah said a half and a
quarter, חצי נזק ורביע נזק קתני. Chatzi nezek u-revi'a nezek katani. אלא
אמר רבא Ela amar Rava so what's פשט pshat in the משנה
Mishnah where it says you get half from the cow and a
quarter from the fetus, which רבא Rava says means a half and
a quarter of the full damages. לעולם בפרה וולד דחד. Le-olam be-parah
ve-valad de-chad.
Okay, we don't it's the cow and the fetus is owned by
the same person. So what's the issue? Just collect everything from the
cow. והכי קאמרינן Ve-hachi ka-amrinan and here is what we're saying. איתא
לפרה משתלם חצי נזק מפרה, Ita le-parah mishtalem chatzi nezek mi-parah, if
the cow is around and you can't find the fetus or the
fetus is worth nothing, you can get your full half damages from
the cow. These are both owned by the same person, you know
that the cow was the מזיק, mazik, you don't know if the
fetus was the מזיק. mazik. So therefore you are entitled, when it
says a half and a quarter it doesn't mean at the same
time. It means if you have only one of these animals to
collect from you're entitled it's a very simple read of the משנה.
Mishnah. You're entitled to collect your full half damages from the cow.
The cow is definitely the מזיק, mazik, you don't know if it
also had the fetus or not, so all you have in front
of you is the cow, you're entitled to collect your full half
damages from the cow. Of course, why not? Okay, ליתא לפרה, leita
le-parah, however if the cow is not in front of you, it
died, it's worth nothing, it ran away, whatever it is, and the
only thing you have to collect from is the fetus. So then
you if you knew the fetus did it you could collect your
full half damages from it, but since you don't know the fetus
did it you can only collect half of the half, you can
only collect a quarter, משתלם רביע נזק מולד. mishtalem revi'a nezek mi-valad.
So that's a very clean read of the משנה. Mishnah. It doesn't
mean a half and a quarter at the same time, it means
you're entitled to a half from the cow if you can get
it from the cow, if the cow isn't around you're only entitled
to a quarter from the fetus because you don't know if the
fetus was involved or not. And therefore we say split it, it's
סומכוס Sumchos who says split it. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
clarifies, טעמא דלא ידעינן אי הוי ולד בהדה כי נגחה אי לא.
Ta'ama de-la yad'inan i hava valad bahadah ki natchah i lo. The
reason that we say this division is
if the fetus was together with the cow when it gored or
not. cow and the cow gored or not. אבל Aval אי פשיטא
לן ee pishita lan דהוי ולד dehavei vlad בהדי כי נגחה, bahadei
kinachah,
it was obvious that the fetus was together when it gored, משתלם
כולי חצי נזק מהולד. mishtalem kulei chatzi nezek meivlad. You would be
entitled to get all of it from the fetus. Okay, why not?
It was part of the goring animal, why shouldn't you? So the
גמרא Gemara just says, well let's take a look.
So רבא לטעמיה, Rava letaamei, so that idea that if you know
the fetus was part of it, you could collect your full damages
or your full half damages from the fetus. רבא Rava is going
according to his reasoning, דאמר רבא, deamar Rava, פרה שהזיקה גובה מולדה.
parah shehizikah goveh meivladah.
If a cow, a pregnant cow gored, you can collect the whole
damages from the fetus if there's enough to collect from. מאי טעמא?
Mai taama? So that's the same idea here. If you knew the
fetus was part of it, you could collect fully from the fetus
because you don't and you only have the fetus in front of
you, you collect half. Now מאי טעמא, mai taama, what's the reason?
גופא היא. gufah hi. It's all part of the same body. Basically
תוספות Tosafot discusses what the גמרא Gemara is really looking for, the
words it seems the גמרא Gemara is looking for is עובר ירך
אמו ubar yerech imo or not, right? Is the fetus considered to
be a limb of the mother? So תוספות Tosafot discusses why it
doesn't say that because תוספות Tosafot basically says there are when do
you say עובר ירך אמו ubar yerech imo or not, you know,
and like it depends on the circumstances. So תוספות Tosafot sort of
discusses that. If we have a minute, we'll look at תוספות. Tosafot.
But I want to just point out something before you get to
a simple, like why it couldn't use a different phrasing which is
more common is what's the alternative here? Let's say you did not
say that it was גופא היא. gufah hi. Let's say you said
the ולד vlad was some other entity, okay? So what would be
the הלכה? halachah? Let's say I had two cows or whatever, two
oxen that gored a cow, okay? And we had discussed this yesterday.
But we had a, all right. And you didn't, and it caused
a hundred dollars of damage, each ox was worth a hundred dollars.
And you didn't have ox number one around, okay? Could you collect
your full hundred dollars from ox number two? If they were both
owned by the same person, right, would you say that, you know,
each ox, you're only entitled to fifty dollars from each ox, right,
because תם tam is חצי נזק מגופו chatzi nezek migupo or whatever,
there were two goring, or would you basically say like no, especially
if, you know, it's sort of like the question we asked yesterday,
right? Maybe I'm entitled to, if I can't get from one, I
guess from the other. So yesterday it sounded like yesterday we said
that it was the first thing, that if they were really of
two separate people, right, you would have to divide. I could get
fifty dollars from ראובן, Reuven, fifty dollars from שמעון. Shimon. If שמעון
Shimon's ox isn't around, I can't go and collect the rest from
ראובן. Reuven. They really divide equally. Here we're saying what if they
actually both belong to ראובן, Reuven, okay, but one of the oxen
wasn't around. Could I say, look ראובן, Reuven, you owe me a
hundred bucks, all right, instead of collecting fifty from this ox and
fifty from this, I'm going to collect the whole hundred from that?
So it sounds like the גמרא Gemara would say even that case
you can't say. If they were both involved, then you only collect
proportionally from each one and if one isn't around you can't collect
from the other. And that's why the גמרא Gemara says according to
רבא, Rava, the idea that if the mother wasn't around you could
collect all of it from the fetus shows we don't consider them
as two separate oxen because if we considered them as two separate
oxen, then if the mother wasn't around you couldn't collect the rest
from the fetus. You could only collect the proportional amount from the
fetus. But if it's all one ox, okay, then if it's all
one ox that gores and half it dies and half of it
gets taken, half of it gets
taken away, I can still collect the rest from the other half,
okay? So the גמרא Gemara says because רבא Rava is saying you
have the right to collect everything from the fetus if the fetus
was a part of it, that shows we consider it to be
one body. So the גמרא Gemara now has taken what it was
assuming yesterday and has gone one step further, which is two oxen
gore, if it's owned by two people, I can't say hey I
can't find ראובן Reuven I'm going to get all of it from
you שמעון. Shimon. Even if it's owned by one person, I can't
say I can't collect all from one ox,
I'm going to get all of it from the other ox. You
have to divide it equally. And the only reason here you're entitled
to collect all of it from the fetus is because we view
it all as one animal and therefore you're just collecting from different
parts of the animal, okay? So it's interesting that the גמרא Gemara
makes those assumptions that you know about when you would be entitled
to go to the other ox and it says basically you wouldn't
if they were really separate oxen, okay? Yes. But I thought this
was like this was the משנה Mishnah we had, so... yeah. But
the question is how do you interpret the משנה? Mishnah? Based on
this interpretation, that's what emerges. Okay maybe other interpretations. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this, okay, תנו רבנן, tanu rabbanan, now
the גמרא Gemara says like this, דאמר רבא, deamar Rava, פרה שהזיקה
גובה מולדה, parah shehizikah goveh meivladah, מאי טעמא? mai taama? גופא היא.
gufah hi. So it's all one thing and therefore if you can't
collect from part you can collect the full amount from the rest.
תרנגולת שהזיקה, tarnegolet shehizikah,
let's say a chicken gored, damaged, I mean it didn't say gored
but whatever it did, okay, and it would have to be a
case of a קרן keren I guess because it's talking about the
body of the chicken, but it intentionally went ahead and I don't
know pecked away at some plate glass window and broke it or
something, okay, אינה גובה מביצתה, einah govah mibeitzatah, okay,
you can't collect from the egg of the chicken that was within
the chicken when it gored. That would be the parallel. of the
fetus. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? פירשא בעלמא הוא. pirsha b'alma hu. It
is only like refuse, meaning it is not considered part of the
body. It's some thing that's in the body, but it's not considered
a part of the body. Now that's actually interesting because there's other
places in which we consider it to be part of the body,
like if the animal's a טריפה, treifa, the egg also is considered
a טריפה treifa as opposed to something distinct from the animal. So
תוספות Tosafot says it depends on its degree of development. While it's
developing in the, in the mother, then it is in the hen,
it is considered to be part of the hen, and if the
mother becomes a טריפה, treifa, the egg does. But after it's fully
developed and it's just waiting to be laid, right, then it would
be considered to be separate from the mother. And obviously in this
case presumably you don't consider the egg to be a מזיק. mazik.
I mean it's actually an interesting question, why don't, why don't we
say that we collect proportionally from the egg, okay? We don't collect
the full amount from the egg, but let's say you have two
מזיקים mazikim here, a hen and the egg. So presumably it's not
if it's not a live being. It is interesting, right, that before
we saw that you could consider as a fetus to be like
a separate מזיק. mazik. But nobody is saying that you consider once
the egg is not part of the mother, you don't consider the
egg to be a separate מזיק. mazik. So presumably because it's not
live, but the fetus could have been a miscarriage, could have been
born dead. I don't fully get that. Maybe the egg is more
of a separate thing from the body than, than the fetus is,
right, in that like it's not its own entity until it's been
fertilized and hatched and whatever. Whereas a fetus you could like look
in there and it's two things. Right. It has its own whatever
control or, and but an egg is like actually... you wouldn't take,
you wouldn't say a woman's egg... You're saying because a fetus is
alive, I was saying because a fetus is alive, that's why the
גמרא Gemara was more willing to consider it to be an independent
מזיק. mazik. But you're saying that's also why it has a little
more independence from the mother. But once the egg is formed and
has the shell on it and hasn't been laid yet, that's the
stage at which תוספות Tosafot is saying that. Right, so תוספות Tosafot
says, well maybe it hasn't been formed yet, but then it's supposed
to become המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה. Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah. Like I'm
trying to say it wasn't yet formed and I have a right
to collect from it, and you're saying prove that to me, I
say it was and you don't have a right to collect from...
Exactly, a picture. Well maybe then how many days later it got
laid. Okay.
ואמר רבא, V'amar Rava, now רבא Rava also says, אין שמין לפרה
בפני עצמה ולולד בפני עצמו. ein shamin leparah bifnei atzmah ulevlad bifnei
atzmo. Okay, so that's like pretty much ends our discussion about the
goring cow. And again, very interesting in this question of number one
is like an עובר ירך אמו. ubar yerech imo. Number two, when
there are two entities that gore, how much is it divided? How
much is it that if you can't, the גמרא's Gemara's presumption that
if you can't collect from one, you can't collect the balance? I
mean, you, each one is only liable for their portion of it.
So therefore if this were two entities, you could not collect everything
from the וולד. vlad. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara goes on to
a different point. ואמר רבא, V'amar Rava, רבא Rava also says, אין
שמין לפרה בפני עצמה ולולד בפני עצמו אלא שמין לולד על גבי
פרה. ein shamin leparah bifnei atzmah ulevlad bifnei atzmo ela shamin levlad
al gabi parah. Now this is something that we haven't really discussed
yet, but it's also relevant to the earlier discussion about דמי ולדות
dmei vladot when a woman is hit and she miscarries, and we'll
have to go ahead and revisit this when we see that. But
if now this cow was gored, and you know it was gored
by this ox, there's no question what happened. I mean, it's similar
to the משנה, Mishnah, but here you know everything that happened and
you want to figure out how much do I owe
for the loss of the fetus because it's gored this cow and
it made it miscarry. So רבא Rava does say you don't go
ahead and assess, well, how much would you pay for like a
fetus that was about to be born in two weeks? Okay? What
you do is you say no, you look at how much would
you pay for a pregnant cow and how much is it now
you've got a dead cow, it's dead with its fetus being dead.
Okay? And because you're sort of considering it together with the cow,
you're not going to, you're not going to wind up paying as
much. Okay,
אין שמין לפרה בפני עצמה ולולד בפני עצמו אלא שמין לולד על
גב פרה. ein shamin leparah bifnei atzmah ulevlad bifnei atzmo ela shamin
levlad al gav parah. שאם אי אתה אומר כן, She'im iy attah
omer kein, if you don't say that,
נמצא אתה מחליש את המזיק. nimtza attah machlish et hamazik.
The מזיק mazik loses out too much. Now, of course, the question
is, oh, poor
מזיק. mazik. The point is not just that he pays more, but
he pays, it's unfair that he pays more because fundamentally he gored
a pregnant cow, so you should assess the value of a pregnant
cow, you shouldn't assess the components separately. Okay. Which is sort of
like, you know how like you say like whenever you do any
any home improvement, like you never and then to sell the and
then you sell the home or sell the apartment, like you only
get back a small portion of the extra money you put in,
right? What it actually, I mean, different parts of your house you
get a bigger portion of how much money you put, but once
it's part of a larger package you don't fully realize the individual
cost of each thing. Okay? So let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says. Okay. וכן אתה מוצא בקוטע יד עבדו של חבירו. Vechein attah
motzei bekoteia yad avdo shel chaveiro. Okay, אוי, Oy,
so this is you cut off the slave, the arm of a
slave. Okay, now, what would be the... Of course you're paying for
how much is a whole slave worth and a slave without an
arm worth. Like what do you mean you assess the value of
the arm by itself? How would you even do that if you
wanted to do that? So רש"י Rashi says, well what you would
do is you would actually, if the alternative is, תוספות Tosafot says,
רש"י Rashi says, אין שמין את היד בפני עצמה לומר כמה אדם
רוצה ליטול לקטוע יד עבד כזה. Ein shamin et hayad bifnei atzmah
lomar kama adam rotzeh litol likto'a yad eved kazeh. Like he would
say to someone like, okay, how much would you let me pay
you to give me the right to chop off your slave's hand?
That would be assessing the value of the arm by itself. Because
obviously somebody would make up a very high price and they really
would resist that, but once you're already, I don't know, anyway, it's
obviously any of these גמרות Gemaros are always deeply problematic because of
the way it commodifies, you know, a human being here. But besides
which, it's like harder to imagine how you even talk about a
market price of a hand by itself.
Okay, וכן אתה מוצא במזיק שדה של חבירו. V'chen atah motzei b'mazik
sadeh shel chaveiro. And this actually is something we actually had a
few right, remember, by שם, sheim, where it says וביער בשדה אחר
שמין אותה על גב שדה אחר. u'bi'er b'sadeh acheir, shamin otah al
gav sadeh acheir. Right?
If an animal goes ahead and goes into a field and eats
like, you know, some of the whatever, you know, the vegetation or
the grain or whatever, you say okay, it destroyed like an acre
of, it destroyed I don't know, like you know, a pound of
a wheat. How much is a pound of wheat worth? And you
say no, no, no. How much was the field worth before, and
how much is the field worth now? What do you look at
as the object that was damaged? Do you look at it
as the wheat or do you look at the larger object here
as the field? All right, and presumably now again what's the basis
for this is not being spelled out. Let's take a look. So
that's what the גמרא Gemara is about to ask. אמר ליה רב
אדא בר אבא לרב אשי Amar lei Rav Adda bar Abba l'Rav
Ashi ואי דינא הוא, v'i dina hu, if this is the right
law that you should say actually one minute, it killed a fetus,
how much is the fetus worth? So לחש מזיק, lechashmazik, let the
מזיק mazik lose out. What,
what's the logic? Meaning don't just tell me oh the other way
is more the מזיק mazik pays more. Okay, but why do you
choose one over the other? משום דאמר ליה פרה מעוברת אזקתיך פרה
מעוברת שמנא לך. Mishum d'amar lei parah me'ubertah aziktech, parah me'ubertah shamna
lach. Because the מזיק mazik can say look, I destroyed or I
damaged a pregnant פרה, parah, assess for me a pregnant פרה. parah.
Okay, which basically means that makes sense, right? It's basically the point
is the thing that was damaged was the פרה. parah. Now when
you have a pregnant פרה parah and something happens and it miscarries,
whatever, you'll obviously there look at the ולד velad as part of
the פרה parah and you look at the damage fixed as the
פרה. parah. You know, the interesting thing is by the field. You
know, but presumably it's the same thing. Even if you're going to
harvest and you're going to get all this money from the field,
right now you look at it as a field that's ready to
be harvested. You don't look at it as I got some ground
here and I got some grain here and you destroyed the grain.
No, you destroyed, you know, my field that was with this grain
and now it's a different type of a field. So, but yes.
Exception could be saying I was about to take that grain to
market and sell it and you just, now I'm out. Right, so
there is an interesting question which is when would we say like
כל העומד לקצור כקצור דמי, kol ha'omed liktzor k'katzur dami, and like
it was ready to be harvested then at that stage you might
not look at it as part of the field. There is a
stage when it gets to be that way, that's correct. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says now as follows: פטמא פרה דחד וולד דחד
פטמא לבעל פרה. Pitma, parah d'chad u'velad d'chad, pitma l'ba'al parah. Now,
let's say you go ahead
and the, you now have to pay off the,
your ox gored a pregnant פרה parah and you have to pay
the person. But the ולד velad was owned by somebody else. So
you have to determine how to assess, you know, who basically how
to pay each person for their portion, okay? So we just talked
about that. Well there we talked about how to assess the total
damage, but now we're talking about how to divide it between which
portion of this, this pregnant פרה parah is worth a thousand dollars,
okay, and how much of that thousand dollars goes to the owner
of the ולד. velad. Now what you should have just said is
well how much would it have been worth without the ולד? velad?
Without the ולד velad it would have been worth 800, so 200
dollars goes to the ולד. velad. I know, so let's read what
the גמרא Gemara says. Okay, so פרה parah okay, פטמא פרה דחד
וולד דחד פטמא לבעל פרה. pitma, parah d'chad u'velad d'chad, pitma l'ba'al
parah.
The fattiness is to the owner of the פרה. parah. Let's look
at רש"י Rashi says this means. פטמא, Pitma, רש"י Rashi says: מה
ששמנוהו שהיה יפה מפני שומנו הוי דבעל פרה דולד מחמתו לא אתי
שומנא. mah she'shamnu'u she'haya yafeh mipnei shumno, havei d'ba'al parah, d'velad machmato
lo ati shumno.
So רש"י Rashi says if you've got this פרה parah that's now
because it's pregnant, you know, it's fatty, it actually has put on
weight. So you don't say wow it put on weight because it's
eating for two. It doesn't matter, right? Right now nevertheless that weight
is the weight of the mother, it's not the weight of the
ולד. velad. So that extra value that it has because of its
additional weight, right if you imagine it, meaning the point is you
have to imagine how much would this be worth without the ולד.
velad. But what are you imagining without the ולד? velad? If it
was without the ולד velad and it was its pre-pregnancy weight, okay,
or without its ולד velad and with its current weight? So רש"י's
Rashi saying well without the ולד velad with its current weight, because
the weight is still on the פרה, parah, it's not the weight
of the ולד. velad. So you don't imagine how much it was
worth before it was pregnant, you imagine how much it would be
worth without the ולד velad with the current weight. What?
You'll like it's different in people trying to lose their weight after
they got pregnant.
So how do you assess it?
I don't know, so you imagine what would it be worth minus
the fetus with its current weight. You go out and you ask
people who are in the market, what would you pay for it
with this weight without the fetus? Okay. רב אחא, Rav Acha, now,
נפחא מאי? nafcha mai? How about the fact though that it looks
bigger? Okay, it's volume. So it's actually not its weight, but you
know, people pay more for something that looks bigger. Okay? So that
presumably is because of the fetus that it looks bigger even though
it's actually not the value, the direct value of the fetus, it's
an appearance of the cow. So רב פפא אמר לבעל פרה: Rav
Papa amar leba'al para: So for the fact that it looks like
a big cow, right, you would imagine how much would it be
worth with not only this weight, but this weight but this volume
if it wasn't carrying a fetus? Okay. And therefore that's the amount
that you pay, you pay the owner of the cow. רב אחא
בריה דרב איקא אמר חולקין. Rav Acha brei deRav Ika amar cholkin.
No, you split it, because that additional volume is also seen as
attributed to the fetus, so the owner of the fetus gets whatever
the increase in price is due to that, or at least partly.
והלכתא חולקין, Vehilchata cholkin, the הלכה halacha is you split it. Okay,
I mean if people know what they're doing, why would you pay
for volume if it didn't actually imply weight? I don't know, but
okay. It's always possible to weigh a cow. Well that's true, those
are pretty big scales. Right, that's true. I mean, what? Marketing, we're
seeing.
Right, there you go,
exactly. Alright, so that was the end of the pregnant cow.
Alright, next משנה. Mishnah. Okay, now we make a significant shift, it's
always so funny like how sometimes the משנה Mishnah is like, you
know, it belongs to the previous פרק. perek. I mean it was
a new idea but it was still goring cows, this first משנה
Mishnah in this פרק. perek. And now we're onto something, we're going
beyond the goring cows, we're getting back to more general issues. Let's
take a look. הקדר שהכניס קדרותיו לחצר בעל הבית. Hakadar shehichnis kedeirotav
lachatzar ba'al habayit. So a potter who brought his pots into the
domain, into the yard of the בעל הבית, ba'al habayit, שלא ברשות,
shelo birshut, the owner didn't say you can come in, this guy
was a door-to-door salesman and he just walked in without permission of
the owner and with all his
pots, ושברה בהמתו של בעל הבית. veshivra behemto shel ba'al habayit. And
the owner of the בעל... ba'al... the cow of the owner of
the house owner went and broke it. It's basically like a type
of a רגל. regel. פטור, Patur, he's exempt. This guy is שלא
ברשות, shelo birshut, you know basically we learned that any damage that
occurs in the רשות reshut of the מזיק, mazik, you're exempt. שורך
ברשותי מאי בעי, Shurcha bivershuti mai ba'ei, whoever gave you permission to
be here? I have no liability for if you, you know, if
you're on my property without permission. So I'm exempt. Okay. Anyway it's
רגל, regel, and רגל regel is only חייב chayiv בחצר הניזק. b'chatzer
hanizak. Certainly it's going to be פטור patur ברשות המזיק. b'reshut hamazik.
Alright. ואם הוזקה בהם בעל הקדירות חייב. Ve'im huzka bahem ba'al hakedeirot
chayiv. If let's say my animal slipped on your pots that were
in my property without permission, you're liable. Presumably that's a type of
a בור, bor, right, right, you know you leave your pot, my
animal slips on it. We had a debate before whether it's בור
bor or שור, shor, whatever it is, but anyway you made your
בור bor or you have your שור shor in a place where
you don't have rights, so my animal slips on it, you're liable.
Okay. ואם הוזקה בהם בעל הקדירות חייב. Ve'im huzka bahem ba'al hakedeirot
chayiv. ואם הכניס ברשות. Ve'im hichnis birshut. Now if I say sure
you can come in and bring in your pots, I'd like to
see what you have for sale. So then בעל החצר חייב. ba'al
hachatzer chayiv. Then if my animal steps on them, I am חייב.
chayiv. Now, here we're going to pause for a moment and let
me ask you, why am I חייב? chayiv? I said sure, come
on in, bring your pots, you bring in your pot, my animal
tramples on them, I'm חייב. chayiv. So why am I חייב? chayiv?
What do you think?
The most obvious thing to say is it would be רגל. regel.
I'm חייב chayiv because my animal breaks your pots. Okay, but a
רגל regel is only חייב, chayiv, where's a רגל regel חייב? chayiv?
ברשות ה... b'reshut ha... no, ברשות הרבים birshut harabim it's פטור, patur,
it's חייב ברשות הניזק. chayiv b'reshut hanizak.
So all of a sudden because I let you bring your pots
into my yard, it's considered your yard? It's רשות הניזק? reshut hanizak?
Like it's at most it's both of our yards. Why am I
חייב chayiv for רגל? regel? So it's not so... maybe it is,
maybe that makes it רשות הניזק, reshut hanizak, I let you put
it down, where you put it down in my house is like
your רשות, reshut, but that's a little strange. רגל regel is only
חייב ברשות הניזק. chayiv b'reshut hanizak. So what the גמרא Gemara is
going to say is, not to ruin the surprise, what the גמרא
Gemara is going to say is when I say sure you can
come in, then I am implicitly taking responsibility for anything that happens
to your things. Okay, when I... so
it's actually like even higher liability. I'm letting you come into my
domain, it's my yard, so I am basically saying I am taking
responsibility now for things that will happen to your objects if I'm
allowing you to come in. Your insurance policy is going to cover
it. Exactly. So that... so it's not clear in the משנה, Mishnah,
you could have said רגל, regel, but רגל regel is a little
strange. It sounds like once I give you permission, I am now
accepting responsibility for them. You can always stipulate, you know. Right, you
could always stipulate, correct. Like the guy who made his part of
his yard רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, but like we said he can
stipulate that he doesn't... he's not actually responsible for damage. Right, you
mean when he like gave the edge of his yard to the
רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. Right, I mean here you could definitely stipulate.
But it sounds like the סתם stam is you're accepting liability. Okay,
now similarly this next case is going to be almost exactly the
same except it's going to go basically this משנה, mishna, now that
we've done שן, shen, רגל, regel, and קרן, keren, this משנה mishna
is a little שן, shen, רגל, regel, and קרן keren משנה. mishna.
So הכניס פירותיו לחצר בעל הבית, hichnis perotav lechatzer ba'al habayit, now
let's say you brought your fruit into the house, into the guy's
yard, שלא ברשות shelo birshut without permission, ואכלתן בהמתו של בעל הבית,
ve'achaltan behemato shel ba'al habayit, and he ate it, פטור, patur, he's
exempt, the owner, because it's like a רשות המזיק reshut hamazik who
gave you permission to be here. Okay, ואם הוזקה בהן בעל הפירות
חייב, ve'im huzka bahen ba'al haperot chayav, and if it slipped on
it, so it's a type of a בור, bor, you're liable, you
brought your fruit here without permission. ואם הכניס ברשות, ve'im hichnis birshut,
I gave you permission, then and then my animal ate it, that's
שן, shen, okay, בעל החצר חייב, ba'al hachatzer chayav, then I'm חייב.
chayav. Okay,
so again we went from רגל regel to שן, shen, but again
it's not רשות הניזק, reshut hanizak, so presumably I'm חייב chayav because
I implicitly accepted liability. הכניס שורו לחצר בעל הבית, hichnis shoro lechatzer
ba'al habayit,
now we're going to go to קרן. keren. Okay, I allowed—you bring
your ox into my domain, שלא ברשות shelo birshut without permission, ונגחו
שורו של בעל הבית, unegacho shoro shel ba'al habayit,
now my ox gores your ox, או שנשכו כלבו של בעל הבית,
o shenashcho kalbo shel ba'al habayit,
or my dog bites it, okay, which is similar, okay, פטור, patur,
I'm exempt. Okay,
that's a case of קרן. keren. Okay, and even though קרן keren
it doesn't matter the domain, if you're in my domain, רשות המזיק,
reshut hamazik, then it's שורך ברשותי מאי בעי, shorchecha birshuti mai ba'ei,
you have no permission to be on—not liable for anything that happens.
Okay, ונגח הוא שורו של בעל הבית, venagach hu shoro shel ba'al
habayit,
if your ox gores my ox, חייב, chayav, you're obviously חייב, chayav,
right? You know, it's a קרן, keren, of course you're חייב, chayav,
and it's in my domain. נפל לבורו, nafal leboro, let's say your
ox falls into my well, והבאיש מימיו, vehev'ish meimav,
and it ruins the water of my well, because I've now got
בהמה behema stink, cow stink in my well, okay,
חייב, chayav, you're חייב. chayav. Now that would probably be like a
type of a רגל regel or something like that. But anyway, again,
it doesn't matter, it's you're in my domain. You're חייב chayav for
what you do. Okay, now היה אביו או בנו לתוכו, hayah aviv
o beno letocho, if the house owner's father or son was deep
in the well, משלם את הכופר, meshallem et hakofer, and it kills
them and it falls in, it pays כופר. kofer. Now the problem
is going to be כופר's kofer only by מועד, mu'ad, why is
it paying כופר? kofer? Okay, maybe this is interesting. According to, you
know, the position that a תם, tam, remember the position that a
תם tam pays full damages when it's in the—when it's in the
רשות reshus?
המזיק—חצר הניזק, excuse me. So would you pay full—would you pay כופר
kofer if you're a תם tam in חצר הניזק? chatzer hanizak,
Right, remember the position that when your animal goes in and does
a goring if it's actually in the other person's domain, it actually
is full, not half? Anyway, this is going to be a question,
why you pay כופר. kofer. Let's finish the משנה. mishna. ואם הכניס
ברשות, ve'im hichnis birshut, but I allowed you to bring your animal
in, then בעל החצר חייב, ba'al hachatzer chayav, and then my animal
gores yours, so I'm חייב. chayav. That's like the obvious case, because
then it's a קרן, keren, of course קרן keren is חייב chayav
once you lose the fact that it's שלא ברשות, shelo birshut, my
animal gores yours and you have a right to be—of course I'm
going to be חייב. chayav. רבי אומר Rabbi omer בכלן, bechullan, in
all these cases, אינו חייב עד שיקבל עליו לשמור. eino chayav ad
sheyekabbel alav lishmor. So this makes it clear—seems to make it clear
why according to the תנא קמא tanna kamma you were חייב. chayav.
All these cases where you say the owner, the homeowner is חייב
chayav when he gave the guy permission and then the pot or
the fruit got damaged, רבי Rabbi says it's not true. The homeowner
isn't חייב chayav unless he explicitly says, 'Come on in and I
will—I'll protect your objects. I'll take responsibility for your objects.' But if
he didn't explicitly articulate that he would accept responsibility, then even if
you give a guy permission, your animal tramples on it, eats it,
or whatever, you're פטור. patur. It's שן shen and רגל regel and
it's not in רשות הניזק reshut hanizak and you're פטור. patur. Presumably
you'd still be חייב chayav by קרן, keren, although since רבי Rabbi
is going on the last case, it sounds like no, but that's
a little harder to understand why you wouldn't be חייב chayav by
קרן. keren. Yes. So I was just wondering about the אביו ובנו.
aviv ubeno. So we're assuming that the reason why that would be
is because the אביו aviv just has a blanket permission to come
into the חצר chatzer whenever he wants? No, no, no. My אביו
ובנו aviv ubeno were there because they live in my property. That
wasn't that they're strangers. Anyway, it wouldn't matter. No, but let's say
fine, no, but let's say it was you that went into my
property. You're not my father and my son and then
the—אביו ובנו aviv ubeno were in the well. I understand that. I'm
trying to understand why it's אביו ובנו aviv ubeno דוקא. davka. It's
just not דוקא, davka, it's just a standard case. I mean, let's
say it was a third party who didn't have right to be
there, would you still be חייב chayav in כופר? kofer? Yeah, presumably—I
mean we'll see—I mean we'll have to figure out why you're חייב
chayav in כופר, kofer, but presumably the only reason time you would
be
פטור patur is—well—well the question is would you ever be פטור patur
in כופר? kofer? Even if I gave you the right to be
in my property, right, why would that—like a—like you have a right
to be in רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim, קרן keren is always going
to be חייב. chayav. So it's not so clear in the end
what the חיוב chiyuv of כופר kofer is only because you don't
have permission. It might be even if you do have permission. We'll
have to see about that. Okay? The cases of אביו ובנו aviv
ubeno presumably is just like a common scenario. It could be anybody.
Exactly. Exactly. It's just a common scenario. Right. Into my yard. Yeah,
yeah, I mean we'll see about it, but yes. Okay, let's take
a look now at the גמרא. gemara. Did you have a question
Jonah? I was wondering why we're not asking why he's פטור patur
on the— It was a little יוסף Yosef and the brothers scenario.
No, I don't know, they were going, maybe it was a well
that I was storing things in and not it was a pit,
not a well, and he was going down to, you know, like,
you know. Maybe he's going to ask why you don't just say
it's the, who's the guy at the end? Which? רבי? Rabbi? Yeah,
why wouldn't he just say it's a שומר shomer then? Why are
we going through this whole thing of bringing in the חצר chatzer
without רשות? reshus
What do you mean? רבי Rabbi is saying, no because what רבי's
Rabbi presumably saying is that the reason תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says
once you give permission, you're liable for damages of that occur to
your guest's property, is because that's implicit acceptance of responsibility. And רבי
Rabbi is saying I don't agree with this implicit acceptance of responsibility.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: טעמא דשלא ברשות. Taama
deshelo bireshus.
The reason that you're liable, the גמרא Gemara is focusing on why
you the guest are liable if the owner's animal gets damaged, is
because you didn't have permission.
הא ברשות, Ha bireshus, but if you were given permission, לא מיחייב
בעל הקדירה בנזקי בהמתו דבעל החצר. lo mechayev baal hakdeirah benizkei behemto
d'baal hachatzer. So let's say I gave permission for the guy to
bring in his pots. The משנה Mishnah never spelled this out about
what happens, the משנה Mishnah says once he has permission, I'm liable
if his pots get damaged. It never said once he has permission
and my animal slips on his pots, is he liable? Presumably he's
not. It says he came in without רשות reshus and my animal
got hurt on his pots, he is חייב. chayav. Presumably if he
has רשות reshus, and he brought in his pots my animal slipped,
he's not חייב. chayav. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, okay, הא
ברשות, Ha bireshus, if you have רשות, reshus, לא מיחייב בעל הקדירה
בנזקי בהמתו דבעל החצר. lo mechayev baal hakdeirah benizkei behemto d'baal hachatzer.
He would not be liable if my animal got damaged. ולא אמרינן
קיבולי קיבל בעל הקדירה נטירותא דבהמתו דבעל החצר, Velo amrinan kibulei kibal
baal hakdeirah netirosa d'behemto d'baal hachatzer,
that just because you gave your guest permission, okay,
why don't we say, well if you gave him permission, he implicitly
is accepting liability. You're being so nice, right, to let me come
into your yard, maybe that should be an implicit acceptance of liability
on my part for any damage that might occur to you because
you've allowed me or my stuff in your yard. We don't say
that, right? So let's figure this out, right? The guy brought in
his pots without רשות, reshut your animal slipped and hurt itself on
it, basically he's חייב chayav because it's a בור. bor. He made
a בור שלא ברשות. bor shelo bireshus. You give him permission, he
put down his pots, presumably he made a בור ברשות, bor bireshus,
like if he had a right to put his stuff there and
your animal got tripped, right? So presumably he's not liable just because,
he's not liable for בור bor in that case. But the גמרא's
Gemara saying but wait a minute, fine, you're not liable for a
בור, bor, but why don't you say look, the guy was nice
enough to let you come in and to put your pots down,
whatever, maybe you were implicitly having to accept any responsibility if something
happened as a result of you bringing your pots in. We don't
say that, okay? So now the גמרא's Gemara going to continue. It
says like this: אימא ולא מיחייב בעל קדירה בנטירותא דבהמתו דבעל החצר,
Eima velo mechayev baal hakdeirah benetirosa d'behemto d'baal hachatzer, מני רבי היא,
Mani? Rabbi hi, דאמר כל בסתמא לא קיבל עליו נטירותא. de'amar kol
bistama lo kibal alav netirosa. So this is רבי Rabbi who's saying
we don't interpret any implicit accepting of responsibility. The same way we
don't assume that the homeowner implicitly accepts responsibility, we don't assume that
the guest implicitly accepts responsibility. So you let me be a guest,
fine, I'm not going to be, you know, accept any particular responsibility
to damage that occurs to you. And if your animal slipped on
my pot, it's not my problem. Okay, so we don't say, interpret
any implicit acceptance of responsibility.
אימא סיפא, Eima seifa, let's look at the end. הכניס ברשות בעל
החצר חייב. Hichnis bireshus, baal hachatzer chayav. So the owner of the
house, the homeowner is חייב chayav for responsibility to the damaged pots.
So why is that, right? It would be a שן ורגל. shen
ve'regel. So why is he חייב chayav just because he let the
guy bring his pots in? So what do we say? אתיא כרבנן,
Atia k'Rabbanan, it goes like the Rabbis, דאמרי בסתמא נמי קיבולי קיבל
עליו נטירותא, d'amri bistama nami kibulei kibal alav netirosa, that when you
give somebody permission to come in, you are implicitly accepting responsibility. So
basically, I mean you can yourself figure out the answer. The גמרא
Gemara says like this:
If I give you permission to come in and my animal tramples
on your stuff and damages it, it's not שן ורגל shen ve'regel
because it's not חצר הניזק, chatzer hanizak? but I am חייב chayav
because I implicitly have accepted liability when I allow you to come
in and be my guest. So why when my animal gets hurt
on your thing and I gave you permission, haven't you implicitly accepted
liability for when my stuff gets damaged? If when I let you
come in and bring your stuff in, I'm implicitly accepting liability for
your stuff being damaged, why don't we say the reverse? If my
animal gets hurt on your stuff, you've implicitly accepted responsibility for me.
So what do you think the difference would be? Do you see
a difference? It doesn't make sense to say that. I mean like
the house, it's one, you're coming onto my property at the end
of the day. Right. So basically the logic is, if I have
invited you in as a guest, in my position of being like
the homeowner, right, it means right, I'm in the position. of the
responsible party here. This is my domain, my property. If I've welcomed
you in, then I—that's what hospitality is. It's like I'm taking responsibility
for you, okay? As your guest, you are not taking particular responsibility
for the host. The host is taking responsibility for his guest. So
when I welcome you in and I take responsibility, if something goes
wrong with your stuff, I am implicitly—that's what it means to be
a host, I'm accepting that responsibility. If you implicit—if your stuff leads
to something of mine being damaged, which you otherwise wouldn't be liable
for, your role as a guest is not to accept liability for
anything that might go wrong because you're a guest in my house.
Okay? So that's basically the difference which the Gemara... Now you could
say, "What do you mean? You're the one getting something—you're the one
that's being—you get—that's getting this, you know—you know, you're getting something. You
owe the person something." But that's not the way it works. When
you welcome somebody in as the host, you're sort of accepting, you
know, a certain—the role of the host is sort of being responsible
for the guest and not the reverse. Yes. Intuitively, it seems like
there should be some different scenarios between someone more towards being like
a guest and somebody more towards being like a traveling salesman. Aha.
Right, right. Like if I invite—if I allow a salesman to come
into my house and he brings all of his... That's an interesting
point. You know, I'm not really... Right, right, right.
The difference between like
hospitality and tolerating somebody and hospitality. It's a good point. Yeah, it's
a good point. So anyway, that's what the Gemara is going to
get to. Let's see the Gemara. Okay. So, okay. וזו Vesu רבי
אומר Rebbi omer בכולם אינו חייב עד שיקבל עליו בעל הבית לשמור.
bekulam eino chayav ad sheykabel alav baal habayit lishmor. You have no
liability until you explicitly accept liability. רישא וסיפא Reisha vesayfa Rebbi, so
the beginning and the end where there is no impli—no implicit liability
is Rebbi. המציעתא Hametziata רבנן rabanan and the middle where there is
liability when things happen to my guest, that's the Rabbis. I mean,
you've got to be consistent. Says the Gemara, אמר רב זירא Amar
Rav Zeira תבי Tavi מאן דתנא זו לא תנא זו, man deshuna
zo lo shuna zo, which is never a satisfying answer. You're right,
different positions are floating around. ורבא אמר Verava amar לא כולה רבנן
היא. lo kula rabanan hi.
Except till you get to the last line, it's all the Rabbis.
Meaning Rebbi says you never accept responsibility, the Rabbis say you do
implicitly accept responsibility. וברשות, Uvireshut, okay, שמירת קדרות קיבל עליו בחצר. shemirat
kederot kibel alav bechatzer.
When I give permission, I am accepting implicitly the responsibility for the
pots. ואפילו נשברו ברוח, Vafilu nishberu beruach,
even if I had nothing to do with it, right? It's like
homeowners—like that isn't what homeowners insurance is about? Well, you want to
protect also your property from loss, but it's also if some—if some
guest on your property gets hurt, you can be sued, right? So
when I have somebody on my property and they're here with permission,
I'm implicitly accepting liability if anything goes wrong, even if some accident
occurs, even if it wasn't my cow that ate the fruit, even
if some wind blew over the pots. Once you're a guest in
my house, I'm implicitly accepting responsibility for things that happen to you
and it is not the reverse. You as a guest are not
responsible for things that happen to me. I am the host, I'm
responsible for things that happen to you as the guest. Okay, but
I do accept Zev's point that like it's not always about hospitality.
Okay, now the Gemara continues. הכניס פירותיו, Hichnis perotav, but now we
understand that a guiding principle here is the reason you're חייב chayav
is not שן ורגל, shen ve-regel, it's not רשות הניזק. reshut hanizak.
The reason you're חייב chayav is implicit accepting of responsibility. הכניס פירותיו
לחצר בעל הבית, Hichnis perotav lachatzer baal habayit,
now you brought in your fruit. Okay? And it basically says if
you did it שלא ברשות shelo bireshut and the animal slipped and
got damaged or whatever, you're liable. That's a case of like a
בור. bor. Okay, but presumably if it's ברשות bireshut you would be
exempt. Okay, so now the Gemara says like this: אמר רב Amar
Rav לא שנו—when lo shanu are you liable if you put the
fruit down there and the animal slipped and got damaged and you
didn't have
permission?—אלא שהוחלקה בהן. ela shehuchleka bahen. אבל אכלה פטור. Aval achla patur.
And it got sick, you're exempt. So here's an interesting question, right?
Let's do an even easier scenario. בור ברשות הרבים. Bor bireshut harabbim.
I put my fruit down in the middle of the street, okay,
in the רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim, an animal slips, I'm חייב. chayav.
That's a בור ברשות הרבים. bor bireshut harabbim. Let's say an animal
eats it and got sick. Am I חייב chayav or not? Okay,
so it's not a classic בור, bor, right? A classic בור bor
is—is just like is something that happens to the victim because—when the
victim is not sort of like, you know, accidentally engages in the
thing. Here, the victim, the cow, sees it and consciously eats it,
but and it got sick, but it wouldn't have gotten sick if
I hadn't put it there. Do we call that a בור bor
or do we say that's like גרמא בנזיקין פטור? grama binizikin patur?
A בור bor is when the victim trips over it, slips on
it. When the victim actively sees it and consciously chooses to eat
it, so I might be to blame but only in a very
indirect sense and it's a גרמא, grama, it's not בור, bor, right?
So that's basically what's being said here. In that case you're פטור.
patur. מאי טעמא? Mai taama? הדי לה שלא תאכל. Haday leh shelo
tochal. It shouldn't have eaten it. Now, what does 'it shouldn't have
eaten it' might mean? It shouldn't have eaten it might just have
mean is I shouldn't—I couldn't have anticipated that it would do it.
Which is very funny. Why shouldn't you anticipate that an animal will
eat fruit? So if you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות
Tosafot says: הדי לה שלא תאכל. Haday leh shelo tochal. תוספות Tosafot
says... אין לפרש לכך פטור patur, דחשי כרוח שאינו מצוי *ein lefarush
lekach patur dechashi kiruach she'eino metzuyei*, that it's like something unlikely that
the animal would eat fruit, which is bizarre. Why would that be
unlikely? Maybe it's unlikely it would eat so much that it would
give itself a stomach ache, but תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* says no, that's
not true. Okay, because later on it makes it very clear that
it was a likely thing, so I'm just skipping to the end
of תוספות *Tosafos* after the parenthesis. אלא *Ela* says תוספות *Tosafos* היינו
טעמא *hainu ta'ama* here's the reason you're exempt, כיון שבמכוון מביא עליו
דבר שמזיקו *keivan shebimchkaven mevi alav davar shemaziko*,
the animal is knowingly consuming the fruit which is damaging it, is
participating in its own damage to itself. Okay, אינו ראוי זה להתחייב
בכך *eino ra'uy zeh lehitchayav bekach* you can't make me responsible. It's
sort of like a פיה הניזק *pi hanizak*. Okay, if you're actually
engaging in the thing itself and bringing it upon, the animal is
bringing it upon yourself, it's not like I am the מזיק mazik
*mazik*. Now, you know, of course there's a question like you know
animals are not so intelligent and how much is it its blame,
but nevertheless it's an interesting question like the way I would frame
it, תוספות *Tosafos* makes it sound like a more general principle. You
can never hold me liable to something that an animal sort of
consciously, you know, did to itself. But I would just see that
it's not a בור bor, *bor*. בור bor, *Bor* is something that
happens through inattention and through accident and not through some type of
a conscious type of a thing. I'm trying to think about what
would be another example where it wouldn't be a בור bor *bor*.
Let's say it would be a question of, oh I don't know,
here's an...
let's say it would be a case of אש *eish*. Let's say,
I mean, I have the case because animals tend to be afraid
of fire, but okay. Let's, but let's say it would be a
case that I set a fire and I knew that there was
a certain animal, whatever, there was a reason to expect and I
was negligent that certain animals out there play... are there any animals
that play with fire? Probably not, they're probably all afraid of it.
I'm trying to think of some type of a thing. Anyway, the
point is is just a בור bor, *bor* thing. If an animal
actually did it to itself consciously, but I knew that that was
a likely occurrence of this type of a thing, right, תוספות *Tosafos*
says it's not just technically it's not a בור bor, *bor*. It's
that all of these אבות נזיקין nizikin *avos nezikin* are when there's
the actor, you know, the perpetrator and the victim, the one that
it was perpetrated upon. But when the thing itself takes a part
in its own injury even if it is a, you know, it
could be expected and the animal is not really, you know, hyper-intelligent,
nevertheless that is not the classic example of the אבות נזיקין nizikin
*avos nezikin*. Okay, and even if I'm indirectly to blame, that's like
גרמה בנזיקין *grama binezikin* and I'm פטור patur. *patur*. Alright, so that's
what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. Okay, אמר amar, רב ששת *Amar
Rav Sheshet* so says רב ששת *Rav Sheshet*, אמינא *Amina* I said
כי נים ושכיב רב אמרה להא שמעתתא *ki nayim veshachiv Rav amrah
leha shmeitata*. רב *Rav* must have been, right, רב *Rav* must have
been dozing off when he said this. Okay, why? דתניא *Detanya* because
it's clear that you are חייב chayav. *chayav* in that case. We
taught in a ברייתא braita *beraita*, הנותן סם המות לפני בהמת חבירו
*Hanosain sam hamaves lifnei behemas chaveiro*. If you put poison in front
of your friend's animal, פטור patur, מדיני אדם וחייב בדיני שמים *patur
midinei adam vechayav bidinei shamayim*. You're exempt in court but you're liable
in heaven. Now, that would be a good example. You're not liable
even though you were to blame because it did it to itself.
But he says, but but here's why he thinks that that's a
counter-example. סם המות הוא דהוא דלא עבידא דאכלה *sam hamaves hu dehu
delo avida de'achla*. Why are you exempt? Because it's poison and normal
animals will avoid poison. I guess it depends how obvious it was
that it was poison. I understand. Okay, אבל פירות דעבידא דאכלה *aval
peiros de'avida de'achla*
fruit which is a natural thing, בדיני אדם נמי מיחייב *bidinei adam
nami mechayav* you should also be חייב chayav *chayav*. Again I want
to know what type of a חיוב *chiyuv* it is, is it
a בור bor, *bor*, what is it? Anyway, but he thinks it's
just because it's poison the animal should have known better, but if
it's fruit where the animal should have known better you would be
liable. ואמאי v'amai, הרי לא תאכל *ve'amai harei lo tochal* why did
he say it shouldn't have eaten? So you see you don't say
that, you are liable if the animal eats the fruit and gets
injured. So אמינא *Amina*, הוא הדין אפילו פירות נמי פטור patur *hu
hadin afilu peiros nami patur*. You're also exempt by fruit, so פטור
מדיני אדם *patur midinei adam*. So why did it give the example
of poison? I would say because poison is more deadly. You would
think if you would tell me the two things, I would think
you'd be more liable, you should be more חייב chayav *chayav* by
the poison case. Okay, so you both, you both, והא קמשמע לן
דאפילו סם המות נמי דלא עבידא דאכלה חייב chayav. בדיני שמים *veha
kamashma lan de'afilu sam hamaves nami delo avida de'achla chayav bidinei shamayim*.
Even poison which it shouldn't have eaten, חייב chayav? בדיני שמים *chayav
bidinei shamayim*, you're still liable in heaven, there's still moral liability, okay.
But nevertheless in both cases you're פטור *patur* because even in fruit
which it would more naturally eat is not, is basically you're, you
are not liable. ואיבעית אימא סם המות נמי באפרזתא דהיינו פירות *ve'iba'is
eima sam hamaves nami ba'afarzata dehainu peiros*, סם המות *sam hamaves* could
also be talking about a certain type of a, of a grass
which is actually poisonous which it would naturally eat. It doesn't know
to avoid. Okay, so these are... could be cases where it actually
doesn't know to avoid it and you are פטור *patur* at the
end of the day whether it did or didn't know to avoid
it because you didn't, because the animal did it to itself. מתיבי
*Meseivi*. We're not done. We still want to try to prove whether,
whether you're liable when an animal eats the fruit. האישה שנכנסה לטחון
חטים אצל בעל הבית *Ha'ishah shenichnesah litchon chitin etzel ba'al habayis*. A
woman went to bring in her grain to a grind in, you
know, somebody else's mill house. Okay, and תוספות *Tosafos* says the חידוש
chiddush, *chiddush* here is is that even though she's a customer and
you might think there might be a presumption you have a right
to walk in, no, like, you know, you gotta get permission to
go into, into the person's domain. Okay. So she goes in שלא
ברשות, shelo b'reshut, שלא ברשות, shelo b'reshut. ואכלה בהמתו של בעל הבית,
v'achalta behemshto shel ba'al habayis,
and the homeowner's animal ate it, פטור, he is exempt because she
was there שלא ברשות. shelo b'reshut, אם הוזק, im huzak, if the
animal was damaged with this wheat, חייבת, chayevet, then she is liable.
So now we're assuming the animal was damaged by eating the wheat.
ואמאי, v'amai, why is she liable? נימא הוי ליה שלא תאכל, neima
havei lei shelo tochal,
the animal shouldn't have eaten. אמר, you could say, ומי עדיפא ממשנתינו,
umi adifa m'mishnateinu, why isn't it any better than our Mishnah, דהוחלקה
בהן, d'huchleka bahen, we said it slipped? So which is like a
case of a בור, bor? and that's why you're חייב. chayav So
here too, same case. So מאי קארי לה מאי קארי לה, mai
kari leh mai kari leh, so why did you actually what occurred
to you, what actually made you think that this was a case
of eating and not slipping? So the Gemara says, אמר לך בשלמא
משנתינו דקתני אם הוזקה בהן, amar lach bishlama mishnateinu dikatani im huzka
bahen,
damaged by them, so it means somehow that it's שהוחלקה בהן, shehuchleka
bahen, it means it slipped on them, איהו. ihu. אבל הכא קתני
אם הוזקה, aval hacha katani im huzka, it was damaged, ולא
קתני בהן, v'lo katani bahen,
didn't say with them, it means that somehow it wasn't like an
immediate slipping and injuring itself on it, on it, right, it didn't
slip on it, it wasn't immediately. So אכלה הוא, achla hu, so
we think it means that it ate it דקתני. dikatani. ואידך אמר
לך, v'idach amar lach, the other one said, לא שנא, lo shena,
it wouldn't matter. All right. So we're still arguing that if it
ate it you're not liable, it did it to itself. תא שמע,
ta shema, הכניס שורו לחצר בעל הבית שלא ברשות, hechnis shoro l'chatzer
ba'al habayis shelo b'reshut, ואכל חיטין והתריז ומת. v'achal chittin v'hitriz vamet.
You brought your ox into somebody else's domain without permission and it
ate
their grain and it התריז, hitriz, like I think it means either
what it exploded or maybe it how does it translate התריז, hitriz,
defecated or something or
diarrhea, yeah,
right, so right, so basically it had loose bowels and it whatever
and it died as a result of the diarrhea, פטור. ואם הכניס
ברשות, v'im hechnis b'reshut, but if the owner gave permission then בעל
החצר חייב, ba'al hachatzer chayav, then the owner is liable. ואמאי, why
are you liable? הוי ליה שלא יאכל, havei lei shelo yochal, it
shouldn't have eaten my wheat. So here there's an obvious answer. What
did we just say? Why am I liable when I give you
permission to bring your thing in? Because I accept general liability for
anything that will happen. Okay, it's not because I'm a מזיק in
that case, that's because if I gave you permission to come in
I've accepted liability for everything. So the Gemara says, אמר רבא ברשות
שלא ברשות קא רמית. amar Rava b'reshut shelo b'reshut ka ramit. You're
asking from a case of permission about a case without permission. ברשות,
b'reshut, when I gave you permission, שמירת שורו קיבל עליו, shemirat shoro
kibel alav,
I've accepted liability for everything that happens to your animal when I
welcome you in, ואפילו חנק את עצמו, v'afillu chanaka et atzmo, even
if your ox just strangles itself, anything. Now that's an interesting question,
right, let's say the animal drops dead out of a heart attack,
presumably not, okay, but presumably whatever happens, in a general sense, whatever
happens here in the context of it being on my property, I
accept liability for that. So even if it ate it and it
shouldn't have eaten it or whatever and it did it to itself,
it happened because it was on my property, I accept liability for
that. So that's not an example. But if you don't have permission,
right, then you are not liable and my animal eats your stuff
and you're here שלא ברשות, shelo b'reshut actually in that case you
are not liable. We don't say—and maybe this is also part of
the חידוש, right, maybe the Gemara actually thinks that—because I keep on
saying what would it be, would it be a בור, what type
of a בור is this? But maybe the Gemara thinks that maybe
there's even a heightened liability when you're in my domain שלא ברשות
shelo b'reshut than in all other scenarios. Like in a רשות הרבים
reshut harabbim there's no question you'd be פטור, it's not a בור,
it ate your fruit, that's not a בור, but maybe when you
come into my domain, your violating of my space, it's maybe like
the opposite of when I give you permission. The thing when I
give you permission I accept liability for everything, maybe your violating of
my space means you're fully liable for any damage that comes as
a result of you. That's an interesting idea. Now again I don't
know what category to put it in. You put that in אדם
המזיק, adam hamazik, I don't know, but you could understand that that
actually makes sense. You're not supposed to be here. As a result
of your being here I suffered some damage, I don't care if
you can put it in שור, shor, בור, whatever, you violated my
space and therefore I suffered, maybe that creates a general responsibility. So
I don't know what category to put that in, but that would
be interesting and possible and maybe that's why the Gemara has to
say even that has limits. If it was something my animal did
to itself, brought upon itself, then your liability doesn't extend that far.
But just using שלא ברשות shelo b'reshut. doesn't mean the person that's
coming on is violating it, I mean maybe coming over for business,
I don't have to phone you. Well that's an interesting question, but
do you have implicit permission to walk up to my door and
knock on my door? I mean I can't phone you. Well
I don't know, I mean I don't know what the norms of
the society were. But if people have permission, if when you want
to visit you implicitly people have a right to come up and
knock on my door then that's not שלא ברשות. shelo b'reshut שלא
ברשות shelo bireshut is an assumption that you need to be welcomed
in or else the understanding within the society is that you don't
have a right to come up. my front door, right? So maybe
you do have a right. Or you have a right, but you
better be careful. Oh, that's interesting. Is that שלא ברשות shelo bireshut?
but you accept the liability of the שלא ברשות? shelo bireshut I
don't know. But anyway, but I do wonder why the גמרא's Gemara
thinking you would be חייב chayav here. Is it thinking you're חייב
because of type of a בור? Or is it thinking that when
you enter שלא ברשות shelo bireshut, you accept general responsibility for things
that happen as a result? Okay, let's start the next piece. איבעיא
להו: Iba'ya lehu: היכא דקיבל עליה נטירותא מהו? Heicha dekibel alei netiruta
mahu? דנפשיה הוא דקיבל עליה או דילמא אפילו נטירותא דעלמא קיבל עליה?
Dinafshei hu dekibel alei o dilma afilu netiruta de'alma kibel alei? You
enter into my רשות and I implicitly or explicitly accept responsibility for
things that are going to happen to you. What if those things
that happen to you... Now we already said if a חמקה עצמו
chamaka atzmo or a רוח שאינה מצויה ruach she'einah metzuyah or רוח
כן ruach ken or wind came, all those things I'm liable. But
what if there's three categories: the things that my things does, my
animal eats your fruit, you know, gores your animal, you're my guest.
There's things that happen on its own, a wind blows your pots
down. And then there's things that a third party causes. I welcome
you into my domain, and then Michael's animal comes ahead and gores
your animal in my yard. Am I responsible, or do we say
no, then you gotta go to Michael? I'm sorry, you know, that's
him doing it. That's not my yard that gored it, it's my
animal that gored it. I understand, but do I say when I
welcome you into my yard, I'm accepting all responsibilities? Okay, so דנפשיה
הוא דקיבל עליה או דילמא
אפילו נטירותא דעלמא קיבל עליה. dinafshei hu dekibel alei o dilma afilu
netiruta de'alma kibel alei. תא שמע: Ta shema: דקתני רבי יהודה בר
סימון בנזיקין דבי קרנא: dekatnei Rabbi Yehuda bar Simmon binizikin debei Karna:
He taught a ברייתא in the like נזיקין when they, you know,
in the Tannaitic material that they were learning about נזיקין of this
בי קרנא, be Karna, this ישיבה yeshiva there. הכניס פירותיו לחצר בעל
הבית שלא ברשות ובא שור ממקום אחר ואכלתן פטור: Hichnis peirotav lechatzer
ba'al habayit shelo bireshut uba shor mimakom acher ve'achalatan patur: You bring
your fruits in without permission and an ox came and ate it,
so he presumably the homeowner is exempt. ואם הכניס ברשות, Ve'im hichnis
bireshut, but if he gave you permission to come in, חייב. So
the "he" we're going to assume now means the homeowner is liable.
He's liable to reimburse you for the other guy's cow who ate
your fruit. So the גמרא Gemara says you see he accepts general
liability. מאן פטור ומאן חייב? Man patur u'man chayav? Who's פטור and
who's חייב? רב פטור בחצר וחייב בחצר. Rav patur bechatzer vechayav bechatzer.
It sounds like we're talking about the homeowner. If he gave you
permission... if he didn't give you permission, what... then you go to
Reuven if Reuven's cow ate your fruit. But if he did give
you permission, he is going to reimburse you even though it was
Reuven's cow that ate your fruit. אמרי לא, Amri lo, no, that
we might not be talking about the homeowner. פטור בעל השור וחייב
בעל השור. Patur ba'al hashor vechayav ba'al hashor. We're talking about whether
Reuven has to reimburse you. Okay, so if it's Reuven reimbursing you,
what difference does it make if you have right to be in
my yard or not? So אי בעל השור, i ba'al hashor, if
we're talking about Reuven, מאי ברשות ומאי שלא ברשות איכא? mai bireshut
u'mai shelo bireshut ika? What difference does it make if you have
rights to be in this guy's yard if it was Reuven's cow
who ate the fruit? So the גמרא says no, אמרי ברשות, amri
bireshut, if the homeowner gave you permission to be there, so your
fruit has a right to be there. And then Reuven's cow eats
it, so then הוי ליה שן ברשות הניזק. havei lei shen birshut
hanizak. Reuven's cow is eating your fruit, is eating your fruit in
your domain. Remember, שן shen is only חייב ברשות הניזק. birshut hanizak.
So if I gave you permission to have your fruit here, then
it's like temporarily your domain. You have a right to have your
fruit here. And when it gets eaten by Reuven's cow, he's eating
your fruit in your domain because it's your borrowed domain. I let
you be here. And he has to reimburse you.
שלא ברשות, shelo bireshut, okay, and שן ברשות הניזק חייב? shen birshut
hanizak chayav? שלא ברשות, הוי ליה שן ברשות הרבים. havei lei shen
birshut harabbim. Then he's eating your fruit, but your fruit's in a
place where it's not your right to be here. So it's like
eating your fruit in רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim. בשן ברשות הרבים פטורה
Beshen birshut harabbim patura and therefore it's exempt. So your right to
be or not will determine whether Reuven is חייב for eating your
cow... for eating your fruit. But we have not answered the question
whether when I allow you to be here, am I accepting responsibility
for damage that occurs by a third party. Okay, and we will
continue to see that tomorrow. Jenny had one question? Right, so I
thought we were saying that you do have responsibility and then I
was going to ask if like I have to take you for
the damage but then can I go to Reuven and get the
money? Yes, so that would be possible and תוספות discusses that, but
we have not resolved the question whether I accept liability for a
third party. Right now we're saying that we don't have any evidence
that I do. Okay, so we will continue with that. Okay.